A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2014-2018
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2014-2018
The Library of Virginia
52172, 52853
1.05 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted records in this collection have been flagged but not removed. Types of flagged information may include, but is not limited to: medical records, financial records, vital statistic records, personal information including Social Security numbers, Social Services records, or juvenile court records. Privacy protected documents were sealed and closed in their entirety, but left within the corresponding folder within the collection.
Acquisition Information
Accession 52172 transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 9 January 2018.
Accession 52853 transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 9 January 2018.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariats positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
In 1972, the General Assembly passed an act in 1972 establishing the Secretary of Human Affairs. This office was responsible for management and direction of health and human services provided by the state for the citizens of the commonwealth. In 1976, the secretariat's name changed to the Secretary of Human Resources. With reorganization of state government, the secretariat name changed again to the Secretary of Health and Human Resources in 1988. The Secretary of Health and Human Resources oversees state agencies which provide services to Virginians with mental illness (historically including "mental retardation"), substance abuse and physical disability concerns, and provide assistance to low-income families and to the aging community. Additionally, the agencies also license health practitioners and ensure safe drinking water in the Commonwealth.
William A. "Bill" Hazel, an orthopedic surgeon, served as Secretary of Health and Human Resources during the McDonnell Administration and was reappointed upon Governor Terry McAuliffe's arrival in 2014. Dr. Hazel attended Duke University School of Medicine and completed his orthopedic residency at the Mayo Clinic. He was a former assistant orthopedic surgeon for the Washington National Football League franchise and team physician for the D.C. United soccer team. As Secretary, Dr. Hazel oversaw twelve state agencies and boards: Assistive Technology Loan Fund Authority; Dept. for the Aging and Rehabilitative Services; Dept. of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services; Dept. for the Blind and Vision Impaired; Dept. for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing; Dept. of Health; Dept. of Health Professions; Dept. of Medical Assistance Services; Dept. of Social Services; Board for People with Disabilities; Office of Children's Services (formerly Office of the Comprehensive Services Act); and Virginia Foundation for Healthy Youth.
Other staff members in the Office of the Secretary of Health and Human Services during the McAuliffe Administration include Deputy Secretaries Jennifer Lee and K. Joseph Flores; Special Advisors Pam Kestner, and Mike Wirth, and Policy Advisor Jodi Manz, the contributor and record creator of Series III.
Major policy concerns for the Secretary of Health and Human Resources during the McAuliffe Administration included the expansion of Medicaid in Virginia in connection with Obamacare (the Affordable Care Act of 2010), and the Governors Childrens Cabinet. Governor McAuliffe signed an Executive Order in 2014 creating a cabinet solely dedicated to the education, health, safety, and welfare of Virginias Children and youth. As a part of that effort, the Governor also signed a second Executive Order establishing the Commonwealth Council on Childhood Success. This Council was. chaired by Lt. Governor Northam and focused on improving the health, education, and well-being Virginia's youngest children. The Governor's Children's Cabinet is the Subject of Series I.
Scope and Content
This artificial collection consists of two (2) distinct accessions and contains records created and maintained by Secretary of Health and Human Resources, Dr. Bill Hazel, and his Policy Advisor Jodi Manz during the administration of Governor Terry McAuliffe. The records include Constituent Correspondence, notes, working Files, and Special Project files. The Special Project files consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence, regulations, subject files, legislative files, budget material, and records related to the Governor's Children's Cabinet specifically.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Special Projects and Studies: Governor's Children's Cabinet, 2014-2017 (Accession 52172)
Series II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation - Constituents, 2014-2017 (Accession 52172)
Series III. Records of Policy Advisor Jodi Manz, 2014-2018 (Accession 52853)
Contents List
- Series I. Special Projects and Studies: Governor's Children's Cabinet, 2014-2017 (Accession 52172).
  Arranged chronologically, except for Executive Agreements, filed separately.
  - September-October, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - November, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - December-March, 2014-2015. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - April, 2015 (1 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - April, 2015 (2 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - May, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - June, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - July, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - August, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - September-October, 2015. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Agreements, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation - Constituents, 2014-2017 (Accession 52172).
  Contains incoming correspondence from constituents and other non-governmental entities sent directly to the Secretary of Health and Human Resources or referred to the Secretary from the Office of the Governor for response. Also included is the outgoing correspondence from the Secretary as well as supporting documentation and correspondence from related agency officials. Topics include health insurance claims, Medicaid denial claims, Dept. of Social Services, legislation, environmental health, and mental health facilities.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - January, 2014 (1 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - January, 2014 (2 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - February, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - March, 2014. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - August-October, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - November-December, 2014. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - January-May, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - June-July, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - August-December, 2015. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - January-March, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - May, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - June-July, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - August-December, 2016. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - January, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - February-July, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - August-November, 2017. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series III: Records of Policy Advisor Jodi Manz, 2014-2018 (Accession 52853)., .35 cu. ft. (1 box)
  This box contains a group of seven (7) loose note pads of various sizes with handwritten notes by the Secretary of Health and Human Resources Office Policy Advisor Jodi Manz. The note pads are primarily undated and cover topics found in the rest of the collection.